Guide to the Lee J. Cronbach Papers
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Lee J. Cronbach papers
1940-2001
SC0238
Cronbach, Lee J., (Lee Joseph), 1916-2001.
8 Linear feet
Correspondence, memoranda, articles, proposals, notes, and other files relating to his teaching and committee work and several major publications, including PSYCHOLOGICAL TESTS AND PERSONNEL DECISIONS and TOWARD REFORM OF PROGRAM EVALUATION. Correspondents include Patrick Moynihan, Jack Block, Marshall Cohen, John Feldhusen, Arthur I. Gates, Julian C. Stanley, Vivian Edmiston Todd, and Ralph W. Tyler. Collection also includes reports compiled for the US Office of Naval Research in London on psychological work and research being done in Europe, 1955-56.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Provenance
Gift of Professor Cronbach, 1981, and Janet Cronbach, 2003.
Information about Access
This collection is open for research.
Biographical/Historical Sketch
Lee J. Cronbach made major contributions in the fields of educational psychology and psychological testing. He earned his bachelor's degree at Fresno State College, 1934, his master's at the University of California-Berkeley, 1937, and his doctorate at the University of Chicago, 1940. He taught at the State College of Washington, the University of Chicago, and the University of Illinois before joining the Stanford faculty in 1964, where he was named Vida Jacks Professor of Education in 1967. His research interests were measurement theory, program evaluation, and instruction. He died in 2001.
Description of the Collection
Correspondence, memoranda, articles, proposals, notes, and other files relating to his teaching and committee work and several major publications, including PSYCHOLOGICAL TESTS AND PERSONNEL DECISIONS and TOWARD REFORM OF PROGRAM EVALUATION. Correspondents include Patrick Moynihan, Jack Block, Marshall Cohen, John Feldhusen, Arthur I. Gates, Julian C. Stanley, Vivian Edmiston Todd, and Ralph W. Tyler. Collection also includes reports compiled for the US Office of Naval Research in London on psychological work and research being done in Europe, 1955-56.
Access Terms
Block, Jack, 1924-2010; Cohen, Marshall.; Cronbach, Janet; Cronbach, Lee J., (Lee Joseph), 1916-2001.; Feldhusen, John Frederick, 1926-; Gates, Arthur I. (Arthur Irving), 1890-1972.; Moynihan, Daniel P. (Daniel Patrick), 1927-2003; Stanford University. Graduate School of Education. Faculty.; Stanley, Julian C.; Todd, Vivian Edmiston.; Tyler, Ralph Winfred, 1902-; United States. Office of Naval Research. Branch Office, London.; Educational accountability.; Educational psychology.; Evaluation research (Social action programs); Psychological tests.
Collection Contents
- Papers
  - Personal – historical, 1963-79 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Frankel Archives 1973-75 [correspondence re Cronbach's article "Five Decades of Public Controversy over Mental Testing"] (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Russell Sage Foundation, 1978-79 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Moynihan, Patrick – correspondence, 1975, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - U.S. Commission on Civil Rights, 1974 [proposal for study of school desegregation] (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Carnegie Study for Training Professional Educators, correspondence, 1966-70 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Working paper 16 – (1 of 2) (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Working paper 16 – (2 of 2) (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Project memos, notes, etc., 1959 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Outlines on "A Systematic approach to Generalizability and Reliability", 1959 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Committee of N – working material, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Committee of N – interview notes (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - General correspondence, incoming, A-Z, 1952-1975 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - General correspondence, outgoing, 1952-1980 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence on book about Burt by Hearnshaw, 1979-80 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, outgoing re departmental work, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, personal, including plans for research, 1940-78 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Bechtoldt, Harold P., correspondence, 1958-59 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Block, Jack, correspondence, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Cohen, Marshall, correspondence, 1973-74 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - General correspondence on "Psychological Tests and Personnel Decisions", 1963-65 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - General correspondence: test on the concept function (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Chapters from Psychological Tests and Personnel Decisions (U Ill Press, 1957)
    - Chapter 1.1 – Introduction The Function of Measurement Theory" (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Chapter 1.2 – "Reasoning from Mathematical Models" (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Chapter 2 – "Generalizability" (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Chapter 2.4 "Tests considered as stratified composites" (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Chapter 2.5 "Inferences to variables outside the universe" (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Chapter A "Some Introductory Statistical Concepts" (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Chapter A "Some Introductory Statistical Concepts" (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Chapter A "Some Introductory Statistical Concepts" (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Chapter AA "Joint distribution and composite scores" (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Chapter AA "Joint distribution and composite scores" (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Chapter B "Generalization from Observation to Universe" (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Chapter C "Components of observed score" (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Critiques on book (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Miscellaneous chapter notes (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Comments on Aspects of Measurement Theory (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Comments on social improvement (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Education 354 [Evaluation] syllabus (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Notes for the outline of section II "How Social Actions evolve" (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Notes on construct validation (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Notes on "What are evaluations" (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Report to the incoming VTS chairman (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - ONR London Reports (on European psychological studies), 1955-56 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - ONR London Reports (on European psychological studies), 1956 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - ONR London Reports (on European psychological studies), 1956 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Design for a National Longitudinal Study of School Desegregation: Volume II. Research Design and Procedures, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Comments on Rand Study 1973-74 [1 of 2] (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Comments on Rand Study 1973-74 [2 of 2] (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - General correspondence, A-F, 1951-69 (Box 4)
  - General correspondence, G, 1963-69 (Box 4)
  - General correspondence, H, 1954-68 (Box 4)
  - General correspondence, I-L, 1962-69 (Box 4)
  - General correspondence, M, 1964-69 (Box 4)
  - General correspondence, N-P, 1964-69 (Box 4)
  - General correspondence, R, 1962-69 (Box 4)
  - General correspondence, Sa-Sm, 1965-69 (Box 4)
  - General correspondence, Sn-Sz, 1964-69 (Box 4)
  - General correspondence, T, 1965-69 (Box 4)
  - General correspondence, W-Z, 1962-69 (Box 4)
- Papers, Accession ARCH-2003-218
  - R. E. Snow book:
    - Snow, Richard – c.v. and bibliography (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Lawrence Erlbaum Associates – publisher, 1998-99 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Publication permissions, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - File content [computer disks documents lists] (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Hierarchical models – Michael Seltzer (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Validity:
    - Validity (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Moss, Pamela – validity 1997 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Evers, Colin W. – validity (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Arkansas – email re figures, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Factor analysis paper (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Alpha Project:
    - Alpha outlinks (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - R pages – G.Y. [Coefficient Alpha & Successor Procedures] (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Alpha tapes – transcripts (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Alpha tapes – transcripts (4th copy) (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Alpha tapes – transcripts (master copy) (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Alpha paper – yellow sheets (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Alpha – cassette tapes (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Lampe, James C., email 2001 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Alpha Sources:
    - Guttman, Louis – articles (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Cornfield, J. & Tukey, J. W. – article (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Becker, Gilbert – LJC's comments on article, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - various authors on alpha (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Bohrnstedt, George – article (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Cortina, Jose – article and correspondence, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Gustafsson, Jan-Eric – article (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Authors "L" on alpha (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Livingston and Lewis – articles (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Cronbach, Linn, Brennan & Haertel manuscript – computer disks (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Mislevy, Robert – articles (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Shadish, William – article and letter, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Shoenfeld, Alan H. – article (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Wainer, Howard – article (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Zinbarg, Richard E. – articles 1997 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - General math (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Publications:
    - LJC – assorted articles (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - LJC and Paul E. Meehl, "Construct Validity in Psychological Tests," 1955 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - LJC, "Test ‘Reliability': Its Meaning and Determination," 1947 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - LJC "The Two Disciplines of Scientific Psychology" 1957 and "Beyond the Two Disciplines of Scientific Psychology" 1975 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - LJC "Coefficient Alpha and the Internal Structure of Tests" 1951 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - LJC, articles, 1950s (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - LJC, articles, 1960s (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - LJC, articles, 1970s (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - LJC and Lita Furby, "How We Should Measure ‘Change' – or Should We?" 1970 (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - LJC and Gary A. Schaeffer "Extensions of Personnel Selection Theory to Aspects of Minority Hiring" 1981 (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - LJC, articles, 1990s (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - California Learning Assessment Report, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Books on Demand – correspondence 1989 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Caricature of LJC with accompanying letter by Prof. Fernandez-Ballesteros 1996 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Biographical materials (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - C.V. and bibliography (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Official papers, 1934-1980 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Current solve (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Clauser MV, later MS ["A Strategy for Increasing the Generalizability of Scores for Performance Assessments Scored with Automated Scoring Algorithms"] (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Clauser, Brian – multivariate G theory (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Clauser – G.E.N.O.V.A. (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Clauser rerate [several articles] (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Clauser "A Comparison of the Generalizability of Scores Produced by Expert Raters and Automated Scoring Systems" with letter 1997 and disk (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - National Board of Medical Examiners [correspondence & articles, 1995-2000] (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - American Psychological Society – Cattell Award, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - National Academy of Sciences (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Feuer, Michael, email 2001 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - American Philosophical Society (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - National Board for Professional Teaching Standards (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - National Board of Medical Examiners 1998 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - International Academy of Education (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - National Academy of Education (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - American Psychological Association / Azuma nomination 1994-95 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - American Psychological Foundation (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Museum of Education (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Educational Testing Service (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Professional correspondence post 10/2001 [1 one letter re review of manuscripts] (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Brennan comment [Robert L. Brennan articles and correspondence 1997] (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Cardinet, Jean, 1998, articles and correspondence (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Cardinet, Jean, assorted articles (1 of 2) (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Cardinet, Jean, assorted articles (2 of 2) (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Cook, Thomas D., article and letter (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Linn, Robert L., articles (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Meehl on construct validity (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Shadish, William R., articles (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Mandinach, Ellen B. Integrating Assessment and Instruction for Classrooms and Courses: Programs and Prospects for Research, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Brennan – Generalizability Theory (1 of 4) (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Brennan – Generalizability Theory (2 of 4) (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Brennan – Generalizability Theory (3 of 4) (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Brennan – Generalizability Theory (4 of 4) (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Yen, Wendy M., papers (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - HP programs (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Internet (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Channing House Newsletter 1988-2001 (1 of 5) (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Channing House Newsletter 1988-2001 (2 of 5) (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Channing House Newsletter 1988-2001 (3 of 5) (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Channing House Newsletter 1988-2001 (4 of 5) (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Channing House Newsletter 1988-2001 (5 of 5) (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Christmas family updates (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Copyright materials (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence B (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence C (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence D (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence E (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence F (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence G (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence Gambera (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence H (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence I (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence J (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence K (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence L (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence M (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence Mc (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence N (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence O (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence P (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence R (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence S (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Correspondence T (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Correspondence U (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Correspondence W (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Correspondence XYZ (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Missing data from Iowa State (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Speech June 1993 [information for overhead figures?] (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Untold, untrimmed stats (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Income backup (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Project history (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Miscellaneous April income charts (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Major fields (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Pub - CB (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Elder, Gene, correspondence (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - EDLVL, Ages, LAG (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Comments on 1992 manuscript (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Variable lists (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Dead mtl. to 2/24 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Statistics prior to 2/24 (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - COHx EDL VLxABxAcc (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Stats 800+ cases (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Case IDs (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - List to correct trial (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - Unwanted, trimmed (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Descriptives to April (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - Paper as delivered ["Acceleration among the Terman males: Correlates in midlife and after," 1992] (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - Benbow, Camilla – correspondence 1992 (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - Occup x Income (Box 3, Folder 48)
  - Work entering testing (Box 3, Folder 49)
  - Notebook "BKP REG" (Box 3, Folder 50)
  - Notebook "Alpha" (Box 3, Folder 51)
  - R. E. Snow book: Intro materials (Box 3, Folder 52)
  - R. E. Snow book: chapter 1 (Box 3, Folder 53)
  - R. E. Snow book: chapter 2 (Box 3, Folder 54)
  - R. E. Snow book: chapter 3 (Box 3, Folder 55)
  - R. E. Snow book: chapter 4 (Box 3, Folder 56)
  - R. E. Snow book: chapter 5 (Box 3, Folder 57)
  - R. E. Snow book: chapter 6-7 (Box 3, Folder 58)
  - R. E. Snow book: chapter 8 (Box 3, Folder 59)
  - R. E. Snow book: appendix and references (Box 3, Folder 60)
  - Personal stationery (Box 3, Folder 61)
  - Datebook 2001 (Box 3, Folder 62)
  - Passports (Box 3, Folder 63)
  - Memorabilia, including medals, ID cards, and embosser (Box 4)
  - Diplomas, certificates, etc. (Box 5)
- Papers, Accession ARCH-2004-074
  - Fresno High School yearbooks, 1929, 1930, and Fresno State College yearbook, 1934 (Box 1)
- Papers, Accession ARCH-2008-033
  - Professional Papers, miscellaneous:
    - Miscellaneous correspondence, 1986 and undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Copyright for Designing Educational Evaluations, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Roberts, Arthur, "Ballad of the London ONR" (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Cronbach – C.V. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Generalization theory – correspondence with Torsten Husen and Sandra Johnson, 1984, and paper by Johnson, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Patterson, G. R. – correspondence and paper, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Kane, Michael – correspondence and paper, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Allal, Linda – two papers and cover note, 1980-86 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Cardinet, Jean – correspondence and paper, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Efron, Bradley – Bootstrap material (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Weisberg, Herbert & Bryk, Anthony – correspondence and paper, 1976-79 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Reliability – correspondence, computer printouts and papers (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Rowley, Glenn L., "Application of Generalizability Theory to Observation Studies: Limitation," paper with LJC's notes, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Wittmann, Werner – 2 papers, 1984, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Cronbach – article on him in Spanish, ca. 1987 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - P-D paper (Test Characteristics Affecting Validity and Equal Employment) – draft (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Barnow, Burt & Caine, Glen – correspondence and paper, 1977-78 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Heckman, James – correspondence and paper, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - CRPF correspondence (Cronbach, Rogosa, Floden, Price), 1976-78 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Temptress versions – drafts and correspondence (D. Rogosa, 1978) (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - ANCOVA – drafts of paper and correspondence (D. Rogosa) 1979 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - "Strong Model" and ANCOVA – bibliography and seminar notes, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Keesling, Ward – correspondence and paper, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence re "Analysis of Covariance" paper, 1977-78 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Bibliographic sources on ANCOVA (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Computer printout, labeled "Gary Pgm for P,D" (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Fairness transparencies (possibly for meeting of Committee on Ability Testing, Feb. 3-4, 1978) (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Draft of paper re test characteristics affecting validity (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Schaeffer – notes, figures re frequency distributions (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Lord, Frederick – letter to, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Rubin, Donald B., "Bayesian Inference for Causal Effects: The Role of Randomization," 1977 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Goodrich – copy of his notes on covariables 1977 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Murnane, Richard J. – correspondence and paper, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Campbell, Donald, "Musings on Proglems and Needed Developments Regarding ‘Factorially Similar' or ‘Parallel' pretests in Moving Average and Autoregressive Models," 1977 and Cronbach's "Communication to Campbell, Kenny, and Associates," 1976 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Measurement of change – text correction and references (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Kenny, David – correspondence and paper, 1974-77 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Sörbom, Dag – correspondence and paper, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Covariance – correspondence with Campbell, Snow, Lord, 1966-76 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Test bias, correspondence, 1974-76 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Social Perception and Group Effectiveness – research proposal by LJC and Fred Fiedler, 1951 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Hohn, Franz E. "Some Methods of Comparing Sociometric Matrices" with discussion by Lee J. Cronbach. Bureau of Research and Service, College of Education, University of Illinois. Technical Report No. 5, January 1953 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - NSF. Study Conference on Evaluation, Final Report (Conference director: Lee J. Cronbach), July 1963 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Book reviews:
    - Burt review (reviews by Cronbach and others of L. S. Hearnshaw's Cyril Burt, Psychologist), 1980 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Reviews of LJC's publications, 1978-84 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Book reviews by LJC, ca. 1954-89 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Book review: Handbook of Evaluation Research (Guttentag and Struening) by A Task Force of the Stanford Evaluation Consortium, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Book review: Race Differences in Intelligence (J. C. Loehlin et. al.) by Cronbach, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Book review: Basic Readings on the MMPI in Psychology and Medicine (Welsh and Dahlstrom) by Cronbach, ca. 1957 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Book review: Measurement in Today's Schools (Stanley) by Cronbach, ca. 1955 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Book review: Lives Through Time (Block) by Cronbach, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Book review: The Study of Behavior: Q-Techique and its Methodology (Stephenson) by Cronbach, ca. 1954 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Book review: Mental Tests (Freeman) by Cronbach, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Book review: On the Theory of Achievement Test Items (Bormuth) by Cronbach, ca. 1971 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Book review: Readings in Psychological Tests and Measurements (Barnette, ed.) by Cronbach, ca. 1964 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Book review: The Validity of Occupational Aptitude Tests (Ghiselli) by Cronbach, with related correspondence, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Book review: Handbook of Human Intelligence (Sternberg, ed.) by Cronbach, ca. 1983 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Lee J. Cronbach writings (in reprint, typescript, and other formats):
    - Abilities and Ability Testing: Recent Lines of Thought, reprint 1985 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Alpha coefficients for Stratified-Parallel Tests (with P. Schonemann and D. McKie), reprint 1965 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - CSM tables ("Tables of Mean Item Covariances for Fixed Tetrachoric r's") mimeographed paper, ca. 1965 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Analysis of Covariance in Nonrandomized Experiments: Parameters Affecting Bias, (with Rogosa, Floden and Price), 1977 with its predecessor, Analysis of Covariance: Angel of Salvation, or Temptress and Deluder?, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - An Analysis of Techniques for Diagnostic Vocabulary Testing, typescript 194? (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - The Armed Services Vocational Aptitude Battery – A Test Battery in Transition, reprint, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Assessing Similarity Between Profiles, reprint 1953 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Assessment, typescript 1955 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Assessment of Individual Differences, reprint 1956 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Discurso de Investiduara de Doctor "Honoris Causa" dedl professor: Lee J. Cronbach, Madrid, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Autobiographical article from History of Psychology in Autobiography, photocopy 1989 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Balancing the Qualitative and the Quantitative in Psychological Research, reprint 1986 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Belief and Desire in Wartime, reprint 1944 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Between-Class and Within-Class Effects in a Reported Aptitude X Treatment Interaction: Reanalysis of a Study by G. L. Anderson, reprint 1975 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Beyond the Two Disciplines of Scientific Psychology, reprint 1975 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Can Mental Tests Contribute to Social Justice, prepared for a symposium on mental tests organized by the Sociedad Mexicana de Psicologia, typescript with related correspondence, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Can We Tell What the Lerner is Thinking from His Behavior?, mimeographed conference papers, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 19)